New York Republican State Committee; Records apap119
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Membership Lists, 1896-1984; 2; 1.23 cubic ft.
  - Republican National Convention, 1896-1964; 1984; 2.4
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1896; 1900; 1908; 1912 (Box 6 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 2)
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1912; 1916; 1920 (Box 6 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 3)
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1920; 1924 (Box 6 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 4)
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1928; 1932 (Box 6 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 5)
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1936; 1940 (Box 7 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 1)
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1944; 1948 (Box 7 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 2)
    - State of New York Delegates and Alternate to the Republican National Convention, 1952; 1956; 1960; 1964; 1976 (Box 7 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 3)
    - Temporary Roll of Delegates and Alternates to the Republican National Convention, 1984 (Box 7 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 4)
  - New York Republican State Convention, 1896-1912; 1927-1966; 2.5
    The Roll Books of the Delegates and Alternate Delegates to the Republican State Committee of New York give the names of those who served on the Committee. A handy reference guide, these pocket-sized brochures list the NYRSC chairs, chairs of the executive committee, the secretary, treasurer, and chief clerk and the full New York Republican State Committee. The Roll Books of the Delegates and Alternate Delegates to the Republican State Convention list the delegates from each district in each county of New York that served as delegates and alternates to the Convention.
    - Roll of Delegates and Alternates to the New York Republican State Convention, 1921-1922; 1924; 1926-1928 (Box 7 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 5)
    - Roll of Delegates and Alternates to the New York Republican State Convention, 1930; 1932; 1934; 1936; 1938 (Box 7 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 6)
    - Roll of Delegates and Alternates to the New York Republican State Convention, 1940; 1942; 1946; 1954; 1958 (Box 8 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 1)
    - Roll of Delegates and Alternates to the New York Republican State Convention, 1962; 1966 (Box 8 (2-Membership Lists), Folder 2)
- Ephemera, 1923; 1930-1942; 1944; ca. 1960-1969; 1994; 3; 0.23 cubic ft.
  - Dinner Programs, 1923; 1930-1942; 3.1
    The dinner programs from various Republican events include programs from the 15th District Republican Club Dinners, the Ivy Club Dinners and other Republican events. The pictures contained in these programs would be valuable, as it would allow one to put faces to many names that would remain faceless otherwise. One can also find the names of the Republican Club's officers.
    - Republican Club Dinner, 15th Assembly District Program, 1923; 1930-1932 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 3)
    - Republican Club Dinner, 15th Assembly District Program, 1934-1937 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 4)
    - Republican Club Dinner, 15th Assembly District Program, 1938-1941 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 5)
    - Republican Club Dinner 15th Activities Digest, Report on 40th Annual Ball, 1942 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 6)
    - Republican Association of Rural Counties, Seating Charts and Program, 1939-1940 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 7)
    - Women's National Republican Club, 20th Annual Luncheon, Seating List and Program, 1941 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 8)
    - Ivy Republican Club, Program, 1940 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 9)
  - Political Literature, 1940-1941; 1944; ca. 1960-1969; 1994; 3.2
    This sub-series includes pamphlets, newsletters, and a phonograph record that were given to prospective Republican voters. One finds campaign pamphlets from 1938 and 1944. The 1938 pamphlet is called "Don't Say We Didn't Warn You!" It paints the chair of the Republican County Committee Kenneth Simpson as a reluctant hero who was responsible for bringing morality back to New York after the Democratic Tammany Hall scandals. The 1944 pamphlet is a biography of Sidney Hillman who was the chair of the Political Action Committee and leader of the American Labor Party.
    Also included are newsletters called "Public Affairs" and published by the Committee on Public Affairs for the Republican Party of Monroe County. These cover September 13 through October 29, 1941, the time period from the primary election, where a Republican candidate is nominated, to the general election. The scope of these newsletters is confined to Monroe County. These newsletters provide the committee members of Monroe County with important information about upcoming Republican events, voter information and information about the candidate. These newsletters are meant as guides to ensure that each committee member is knowledgeable about the process of nominating a candidate and how to spread the Republican ideology to the people of Monroe County. This series also includes a campaign phonograph record for Nelson Rockefeller from the 1960s entitled "Nelson Rockefeller Talks with YOU".
    - Don't Say We Didn't Warn You, Committee for Republican Unity in New York, 1940 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 10)
    - A Biographical Sketch of Sidney Hillman, Henry J. Taylor, 1944 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller Talks with YOU, Phonographic Record, ca. 1960-1969 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 11)
    - Committee on Public Affairs, Monroe County, Newsletter, 1941 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 12)
    - National Republican Convention, Political Button "Even More in 94", Form, 1994 (Box 8 (3-Ephemera), Folder 13)
- Rule Books and Manuals, 1939-1984; 4; 0.08 cubic ft.
  This series includes the rulebooks and manuals used by the NYRSC to regulate committee meetings and conventions. The Political Calendar of the Republican Party of New York are included in this series because they provide dates for filing primary petitions, conventions, registration for large and small cities and towns, and what color forms must be used to record these actions. The Political Calendar also supplies the percentage of votes one needs to nominate a candidate for a primary. These span from 1939 through 1963. The collection also includes the rulebooks for state and national conventions. These supply the delegate with the proper decorum for conduct in a convention, explain the functions of each position in the committee, explain the processes of electing and removing officials, and give regulations as to when a meeting must be called. The collection only has the 1976 version of the National Convention Rulebook. The collection also has a training manual for women county vice-chairs of the Republican Party, complete with a series of pamphlets on the subject of learning how to become a community leader, how to manage speakers, special interest groups, and large events, and how to build the Republican Party in one's neighborhood.
  - Political Calendar for New York, 1939-1948; 1953-1961; 1963 (Box 9 (4-Rule Books and Manuals), Folder 1)
  - Women's Division Campaign Handbook and Pamphlets, 1960 (Box 9 (4-Rule Books and Manuals), Folder 2)
  - NYRSC, Rules, 1972; 1978 (Box 9 (4-Rule Books and Manuals), Folder 3)
  - Republican National Convention, Rules, 1976; 1984 (Box 9 (4-Rule Books and Manuals), Folder 3)
- Photographs and Biographical Information, 1919; 1966; 1970-1991; 5; 0.85 cubic ft.
  One of the functions of the Republican State Committee is to act as the provider of positive press on the various campaigns across the state. To achieve this, the NYRSC kept a file of photographs and biographical statements for the press. Although there is a picture of Henrietta Wells Livermore, founder of the Federal Women's Republican Club from 1919, the bulk of the collection is from the 1970s and 1980s. Most of the photographs are marked with the names of those pictured, but there are a few unidentified photos.
  The collection includes photographs or biographies of Richard M. Nixon, George H. W. Bush, Henrietta Wells Livermore, Eunice B. Whittlesey, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Robert Dole, Jacob K. Javits, Malcolm Wilson, and many others.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Abraham Lincoln, Biographical Information, Undated (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 4)
  - NYRSC Members, Identified, Photographs, 1966; ca. 1970-1989 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 5)
    W. M. Anderson.
    James H. Andre.
    George F. Aney.
    J. B. Bixby.
    Anthony Colavita.
    Richard Cosentino.
    Rita Dimartino.
    Kenneth Keeting.
    Charles T. Lanigan.
    Louis Lefkowitz.
    Dorothy McHugh.
    Robert Michael.
    Judson Morhouse.
    Anthony F. Shaheen.
    Sam Singletar.
    Freeman Smith.
    B. John Tutuska.
    Jane Westervelt.
    Eunice B. Whittlesey.
    Forest Wollaber, Jr.
    Fred Young.
  - NYRSC Members, Unidentified, Photographs, ca. 1970-1989 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 6)
  - Chief Justice of Appeals Candidates, Charles D. Breitel, Stanley Fuld, Sol Wachtler, Hugh R. Jones, Dominick L. Gabrielli, Photographs and Biographical Information, Undated (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 7)
  - Delegates and Alternate Delegates, Photographs and Biographical Information, 1972; 1976 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 8)
    Richard M. Rosenbaum, Albany County.
    Wells Stout, Allegany County.
    Manny Gonzalez, Bronx County.
    Gabrielle Gunther, Bronx County.
    Warren Anderson, Broome County.
    Doris L. Brooks, Broome County.
    George Hinman, Broome County.
    Esther D. Twentymen, Cortland County.
    Cyrus Schoonmaker, Delaware County.
    Phyllis Kelly, Erie County.
    Tom McKinnon, Erie County.
    Edward T. Cain, Gensee County.
    Martha Zuris, Herkimer County.
    Elizabeth Cassidy, Kings County.
    Pascual Sanchez, MD, Kings County.
    Carolyn T. Spiegel, Monroe County.
    Joe Margiotta, Nassau County.
    Len Hall, Nassau County.
    Holly Patterson, Nassau County.
    Vince Albano, New York County.
    Joseph Gimma, New York County.
    James Hellmuth, New York County.
    Jack Javits, New York County.
    Bernard Lasker, New York County.
    Louis Lefkowitz, New York County.
    Dorothy McHugh, New York County.
    Janet Havel, Oneida County.
    Shirley A. Jefferson, Onondaga County.
    Hazel J. Field, Otsego County.
    Melvin Klein, Queens County.
    Philip J. Fitzpatrick, Richmond County.
    Carmine Freda, Rockland County.
    John Marchi, Richmond County.
    Frank A. Augsbury, Jr., St. Lawrence County.
    Betsy Kaplan, St. Lawrence County.
    Eunice Whittlesey, Schenectady County.
    Dorothy R. Edwards, Schoharie County.
    Marguerite Getman, Schuyler County.
    Perry Duryea, Suffolk County.
    Brenda Baldwin Wallace, Tomkins County.
    Albert Spada, Ulster County.
    Marie Fontaine, Washington County.
    George Berlinger, Westchester County.
    Owen Peagler, Westchester County.
    Betty Granger Reid, Westchester County.
    Malcom Wilson, Westchester County.
    James P. X. O'Rourke, Winchester County.
    Muriel Butler, Wyoming County.
  - Dole, Robert, Photograph and News Clippings, 1991 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 9)
  - George H. W. Bush, Photographs and Biographical Information, 1973 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 9)
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower, Photograph, ca. 1958 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 9)
  - Renovations of Republican Headquarters in New York, 1991; contact sheet and negatives (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 10)
  - Charles A. Schillings House, Photograph, Undated (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 10)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., Photographs, 1971 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 11)
  - State Conference in Syracuse, Contact Sheets, 1986 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 12)
  - Unidentified Event, Photographs, ca. 1976 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 13)
    Some identified individuals include Senator Camerer, Representative George Farrell, Gordon Howe, Charles T. Lanigan, Jr., Mr. Schoneck (first name unknown), Eunice B. Whittlesey, and Fred Young.
  - Unidentified Event, Photographs, Undated (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 14)
  - Wilson, Malcolm, Photographs and Biographical Information, 1971-1974 (Box 9 (5-Photographs and Biographical Information), Folder 15)
  - George H. W. Bush, Oversized Photograph, ca. 1991 (Oversized 3, Item 1)
  - Richard Nixon at the United Nations, Oversized Photograph, Undated (Oversized 3, Item 2)
  - Henrietta Wells Livermore, Oversized Photograph, 1919 (Oversized 3, Item 3)
- Speeches and Correspondence, 1918-2001; 6; 0.2 cubic ft.
  This series includes miscellaneous speeches and other communications not immediately related to meetings found within the Conventions and Committees series. Other communications found in this series are Nelson Rockefeller's Addresses to the Legislature. Again, these did not occur during a specific meeting, but rather were sent to the various members of the legislature reporting on the progress of the Republican Party during the given year.
  - NYRSC Web Site, Welcome Message, 2001 July 19 (Box 10 (6-Speeches and Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Platforms for the Democratic, Republican, and American Labor Parties, 1918; 1936; 1938; 1940 (Box 10 (6-Speeches and Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Platforms for the Republican Party, 1942; 1946 (Box 10 (6-Speeches and Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, Message to the Legislature and Inaugural Address, 1968; 1970-1971 (Box 10 (6-Speeches and Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Speeches, "Republicans Can Win Statewide Races" by Robert McMillan, 1990 (Box 10 (6-Speeches and Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - "The Electoral College" by William C. Kimberling, 1992 (Box 10 (6-Speeches and Correspondence), Folder 4)
- Films, 1956-1976; 7; 22 reels
  The films in the collection document Republicans and the Republican Party from the 1950s through the 1970s. The films include portraits of Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller, former President Dwight Eisenhower, presidential candidate Barry Goldwater, and President Richard Nixon after his first year in the White House. Four of the films were from the Campaign School Series of the Republican National Committee used in the elections of 1956. The original films were formatted on 8mm and 16mm film. Use copies in VHS and DVD format are available for use in the Department for all of the films except "Portrait of a Senator", the sprocket holes of which were in too poor condition to allow the film to be reformatted at this time.
  - "Campaign Literature", A Campaign School Program, 1956 (Reel 1)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 11:15
    Examples of direct mail and hand-out campaign literature for Republican candidates from the School for Politics of the Republican National Committee.
  - "Defenders of Our American Heritage: Political Party Volunteers", running time: 22:00 and "The Rockefeller Administration: A Record of Progress", running time: 12:50, ca. 1962 (Reel 2)
    Color, use copies available in VHS and DVD, total running time: 34:35
    Narrated by Lowell Thomas; American Heritage Foundation.
  - "Fundraising", A Campaign School Program, ca. 1956 (Reel 3)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 9:30
  - "Meet Barry Goldwater" / "Goldwater Speaks Out", 1964 (Reel 4)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 17:15
  - "New York State", ca. 1975 (Reel 5)
    Color, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 5:20
    11th Annual School of Politics in New York State; same woman as Van Houten (?) film; remarks to young people attending the School of Politics in New York State.
  - "Portrait of a Senator", Undated (Reel 6)
    Fragile, sprocket holes in poor condition and is not reformatted at present time.
  - "Reaching the Non-Republican Voter", A Campaign School Program, ca. 1956 (Reel 7)
    B & W, __ mm., use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 9:28
  - "Republican Basic Beliefs", 1962 (Reel 8)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 11:25
  - "The Rockefeller Administration: A Record of Progress", 1962 (Reel 9)
    B & W, 2 copies of original film, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 12:50
    Narrated by L. Judson Morehouse, New York Republican State Committee Chair. Highlights business, transportation, education, youth programs, and housing during the first years of the Rockefeller administration.
  - "Rockefeller: The Man and His Record", ca. 1962 (Reel 10)
    B & W, 8 copies of original film, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 14:35
    Campaign film for Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller. Includes biographical sketch of Rockefeller and a review of his term in office. Paid for by the Citizens Committee for Rockefeller and Javitts.
  - "Setting a New Course: The First Year of the Nixon Administration", 1970 (Reel 11)
    Color, 16mm, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 38:30
    Jonathan Donald Productions under the supervision of the Republican National Committee. Documents foreign adn domestic activities of President Richard Nixon from 1969 to 1970.
  - "The Time is Now!", ca. 1966 (Reel 12)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 22:30
    Produced for the Republican National Finance Committee. Opens with audio only, no picture for just over a minute. Begins at Capitol in Washington, D.C. and includes footage of various members of Congress. Brief explanation of electoral process followed by further explanation of the two-party system and Republican platform. Featured Republicans include former President Dwight Eisenhower, Governor Nelson Rockefeller, Senator Barry Goldwater, former Vice-President Richard Nixon, Rep. Gerald Ford, various Republican Senators and members of the House.
  - "Town Meeting with Governor Rockefeller", 1969 January (Reel 13)
    Color, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 29:00
    Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller at town meetings in Elmira and Binghamton, NY.
  - Unidentified/Van Houten, ca. 1976 (Reel 14)
    Color, sound is distorted, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 6:25
    Chair of Women's Federation(?) of the Republican National Committee sending greetings to New York meeting.
  - "Rural Voters", A Campaign School Program, ca. 1956 (Reel 15)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 11:10
    Produced by the Republican National Committee. James P. Bigley, chair of Wisconsin Republican Party, discusses mobilizing rural voters.
  - "A Time for Tribute", ca. 1962-1964 (Reel 16)
    B & W, use copies available in VHS and DVD, running time: 18:10
    A tribute to former President Dwight Eisenhower written by James L. Shute and narrated by actor James Stewart. Stewart is featured with Eisenhower at the Eisenhower home in Gettysburg, PA. Includes a review of Eisenhower's early career, World War II, and his presidency.
- Reference Materials, 1888; 1893-1913; 1915; 1917-1984; 8; 122 volumes
  This series contains the reference collection for the NYRSC. The titles in this series have been cataloged in the University at Albany Libraries catalog, but remain a part of the collection.
  - Legislative Manuals of New York, 1888-1983; 1
    The Legislative Manuals of New York were most likely used by the NYRSC as handy sources of historical and current political information. These volumes make it possible to track voter trends as they also focused on the activities of the Democratic Party. Within these compact volumes, one finds a wealth of information about the political make-up of New York.
    One of the major topics covered in these volumes are voting trends in New York counties. From this data, one can find out how many males and females registered to vote and how many voted for Democratic and Republican candidates in the state and federal elections. The Legislative Manuals of New York also include descriptions of state offices and departments and officers who held positions in them. The descriptions include pictures of the officers, short biographical statements, functions of the office and the annual salary. One can also find lists of congressional districts. These lists are an excellent way of determining how congressional districts have changed shape over the years. Finally, these volumes contain interesting facts about New York State, including the origins of county names, the meaning of the New York seal, the state bird of New York, and the dates they were established.
  - New York Red Book, 1948-1982; 2
    The New York Red Book is more of a directory than a portrait of legislative history. Unlike the Legislative Manuals, the New York Red Book does not contain statistics about voter history in a region. These books can be used to determine who served on state committees such as the Board of Education or Health. They also include the tallies of votes for the elections for each state office, who the candidates were and by what margin they won. Some even supply the breakdown of Republican, Democratic and Independent votes. Although the Legislative Manuals and Red Book contain similar information, they differ in scope. While the Legislative Manual gives a broad view of the entire state legislature, the New York Red Book takes a more in-depth view of the representatives. The Legislative Manuals would be useful for statistical data, whereas the New York Red Books are more useful for personal data. The biographies give district, education and family information, political offices and other jobs.
  - Industrial Directory of New York State, 1949; 3
    This book includes a listing of all of the industries found in New York in 1949. The directory lists the address, owners and board of trustees, and the main product of each business.
  - Official Register of the United States, 1952-1953; 4
    The Official Register of the United States acts as a quick guide that informs the reader of the name, title, and salary of each officiating federal officer in the Executive, Legislative and Judicial branches of the United States government. It does not include biographies of the various officers.
  - Congressional Directory, 1953-1954; 1958-1960; 1963-1965; 1968; 1970-1971; 1983-1984; 5
    Like the Red Book, the Congressional Directory gives an overview of the various committees in the U.S. Congress and politicians who led those committees. It also includes data from the sessions spanning back to the first Congress. These books are quick reference guides as they provide the user with a handy tabulated format that allows for ease in paging to the appropriate topic.
  - New York State Constitution, 1942; 1952-1954; 1960; 6
    This sub-series contains copies of the New York Constitution in printed form. They contain a subject list for the body of the constitution, the date articles of the constitution were amended and added, and a detailed index giving the article, section, and page where certain elements of the constitution can be found.